Guide to the Brevoort family papers 1977.285
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brevoort family papers
1760-1879
1828-1847
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brevoort, Henry L.
Brevoort, James Carson
Brevoort family
Brevoort, Henry, 1782-1848
1977.285
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box, 4 oversize folders, and one flat file folder.
The Brevoort family papers contain materials documenting the personal and business affairs of four generations of the Brevoort family, including correspondence, legal documents (estate records, wills, bonds, land conveyances and deeds, and business documents), miscellaneous printed material, genealogical notes, and one scrapbook.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Ruth Wright Brevoort, 1967.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by family member, type, and subject as appropriate.
Biographical note
The first members of the Brevoort family in America came from Holland prior to 1655 and soon thereafter settled in Bushwick, then a separate village that would eventually be annexed by the City of Brooklyn in 1855. After 20 years in Bushwick, the family purchased land in New York City (present-day Manhattan) where the family prospered. It wasn't until 1845 that members of the Brevoort family moved back to Brooklyn.
Henry Brevoort (1747-1841) was a successful farmer whose lands lay just outside of the early city limits of New York. His estate consisted of 86 acres between 9th Street and 18th Street, bounded by Fifth Avenue on the west and the Bowery on the east, thus part of today's West Village. The opening of Broadway up to 23rd Street forced New York City street commissioners to create a dog-leg bend at 10th Street, as Brevoort was determined to prevent the disruption of his estate. Brevoort and son Henry, Jr. prevented the opening of 11th Street between Broadway and the Bowery in the 1830s and 1840s to prevent the destruction of the old family farm house.
Henry Brevoort, Jr. (1782-1848) was widely respected for his adventurous travels and artistic interests. He accompanied Lewis and Clark on their expedition to the Pacific Northwest from 1803 to 1806 and spent a great deal of time in the North American wilderness working for John Jacob Astor's American Fur Company. He was equally at home and well received in salons throughout Europe during his travels abroad. Henry Brevoort, Jr. was a close friend of Washington Irving and was primarily responsible (along with Irving's brother Ebenezer) for the publication of the American edition of Irving's The Sketch Book of Geoffrey Crayon, Gent..
James Carson Brevoort (1818-1887), Henry Jr.'s son, was educated in Europe during his parents' travels. He graduated from Baron Fellenberg's school in Hofwyl, Switzerland and then earned a degree in civil engineering from the Ecole Centrale des Arts et Manufactures in Paris. He served as Washington Irving's private secretary following Irving's appointment as United States Minister to Spain in 1842. Brevoort married Elizabeth Dorothea Lefferts in 1845 and moved to Brooklyn. There he managed the large land holdings of his father-in-law, Judge Leffert Lefferts. In Brooklyn, Brevoort gained renown for his scholarly interest and public service. He studied history, entomology, and ichthyology and also served for many years as a member of the Brooklyn Board of Education and the Board of Water Commissioners. Brevoort also helped to found the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) in 1863, served as its President for 10 years, and was a Director of the Society until his death.
James Carson Brevoort's only child, Henry L. Brevoort (1849-1895), followed his father's interest in engineering and became one of the country's foremost patent and invention lawyers, with a client list that included Westinghouse, Western Union, and the New York and Brooklyn Bridge Company. He was also a founder in 1890 of the Brevoort Savings Bank in Brooklyn.
Related Materials
Minnie Grace Hillard collection, 1925-1986 (ARC.041)
Lefferts family papers, circa 1650s-1970s (ARC.145)
Ruth D. Cruikshank papers (1977.429)
Davenport family papers (1977.345)
Brooklyn, N.Y., Department of Law, Corporation Counsel records (2013.015): Series 1: Case Files, Brevoort, James Carson
Autograph Manuscript collection (ARC.206): Irving, Washington, 3 letters to Henry Brevoort Jr. and Peale, Rembrandt, letter to James Carson Brevoort
Scope and Contents
The Brevoort family papers document the personal and business lives of four generations of Brevoort family members. The bulk of the papers, dating from 1828 to 1847, are chiefly the papers of Henry Brevoort, Jr., his son James Carson Brevoort, and his grandson Henry L. Brevoort. A significant amount of the collection consists of correspondence, primarily letters from James Carson Brevoort to family members, chiefly to his parents. The letters mostly relate to family and school news, although eight letters from 1841 describe an expedition into Quebec Province to survey the area and take daguerreotypes of the landscape.
Legal documents make up most of the remainder of the collection and include estate records, wills, bonds, land conveyances and deeds, and business documents. Many of the documents pertain to the opening of 11th Street (between Broadway and Bowery) in Manhattan.
The balance of the collection consists of genealogical notes, miscellaneous printed material, and a few non-Brevoort items including two pamphlets; a broadside; certificates; a 1791 petition for a cemetery in New Utrecht in Brooklyn; an 1830 playbill; Henry L. Brevoort's scrapbook of news clippings, many on engineering, 1868 to 1874; and detailed Brevoort family genealogical notes, which also include many references to the Lefferts family of Brooklyn.
Family papers; Real property -- New York (State) -- New York; West Village (New York, N.Y.); Families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Families -- New York (State) -- New York; Legal documents; Correspondence; New York (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Conveyances; Estate records; Genealogy; Scrapbooks; New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Eleventh Street (New York, N.Y.); Wills; Deeds; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Bonds (legal records); Travel -- Anecdotes; Canada -- Description and travel; Speeches; Lefferts family; Brevoort, James Carson; Brevoort, Henry L.; Brevoort family; Brevoort, Henry, 1782-1848
- Series 1: Henry Brevoort (1747-1841) (Box OS-6, Folder 1)
  - Receipt, 1818
  - Deed, 1828
    Scope and Contents
    5th Ave/10th St, City of New York to HB, with map.
  - Estate papers, 1836, undated
    1836 will witnessed by Washington Irving and two undated memos.
- Series 2: Henry Brevoort, Jr. (1782-1848)
  - Correspondence, 1831-1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include E. Fellenberg, Henry Brevoort (nephew), and D.W. Lott.
  - Legal Documents, 1833-1843 (Folder Flat File)
    - Bond and assignment of mortgage, 1833, 1837
      HB, Jr. to Henry Cary and James Renwick, trustees for the estate of Laura C. Brevoort. 2 items.
    - Bond and mortgage, 1836
      Jesse Delano to HB, Jr. 3 items.
    - Lease, 1836
      C. Swan to HB.
    - Partition agreement, 1843
      HB, Jr. Elias Brevoort and the trustees of Margaret A. Renwick. Sheepskin parchment.
  - Sub-series 2.1: Eleventh Street (New York City)
    - Printed reports, 1843, 1847, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      By the N.Y.C. Board of Aldermen. 3 items.
    - Handwritten correspondence and documents, 1844-1845 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Correspondents include Isaac L. Varian, J.A. Constant, Robert Boyd, R.F. Carson, Oscar F. Stibbins [Stubbins?], and John Pettigrew. Other documents include undated drafts (including regarding tax assessments), memos, and lists.
    - Broadsides, 1844, 1849 (Box OS-6, Folder 2)
      Tax assessments (1844); Supreme Court hearing on the opening of Eleventh St. (1849).
  - Estate documents (Box OS-6, Folder 2)
    - Will, 1835
      Witnessed by Washington Irving.
    - Letters Testamentary to J. Carson Brevoort, 1848
    - Memo, undated
    - List of his real property holdings, undated
- Series 3: J. Carson Brevoort (1818-1887)
  - Correspondence, 1828-1879 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    From JCB, ALS. 59 items.
  - Title Abstract for Brooklyn property, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Owned by JCB and Elizabeth Dorothea Brevoort. 2 items.
  - Certificates, 1836-1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    4 items: Two from the Ecole Centrale des Arts et Manufactures, Paris (1836 and 1837); one from the New England Historic-Genealogical Society (1858); and one from Williamstown College (1847, oversize).
- Series 4: Henry L. Brevoort (1849-1895)
  - Scrapbook (Box 1, Volume 1)
    Clippings about engineering, railroads and steamboats.
  - Account of a journey to "Northern Woods, Canada", 1873 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    127 pages, handwritten.
  - Speeches on steam engines (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "The Indicator", undated
      61 pages, handwritten.
    - "The Steam Engine", 1874
      120 pages, handwritten.
- Series 5: Brevoort family and genealogy
  - Genealogical notes and ephemera (Box 1, Folder 9)
    In "Ancestral Tablets" genealogical workbook with family tree diagrams. Loose and pasted-in items include a silhouette cutting of Henry Brevoort, clippings, notes and documents.
  - Quit Claim, 1760 (Box OS-6, Folder 4)
    Elias and Leah Brevoort to Hendrick Brevoort.
  - Correspondence and miscellany, 1790-1833 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Power of Attorney, 1790 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      George Shea to Charles McCarty.
    - New Utrecht Burial Ground purchase agreement, 1791 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Farmers Brewery (Brooklyn) business agreement duplicate, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Theatrical Observer", 1830 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      From a Brevoort family trip to London. Has a typed note on the title page.
    - William Brevoort to his parents, 1832-1833 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      2 items.
    - Note on U.S. geography, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)